Guide to the Mexico Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Mexico collection
1522-1995
1770-1865
MS 1776
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
32.5
(80 boxes)
A collection of correspondence; government documents, including reports, commissions, decrees, and awards; church documents; published illustrated materials; maps; and writings and poems from Mexico on civil, military, economic, religious, and social topics. Additions to the collection consist of photographs by Mario Bucovich, maps, and published illustrations.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials have been assembled from various collections and acquired from several individuals. They include materials transferred from the Zeta Collection, Mudd Library, 2004. Transferred from the Latin American Collection Curator, Yale University Library, 2012.
Existence and Location of Copies
Entire collection, with the exception of Accession 2006-M-021 and Accession 2013-M-025, is available on microfilm from Gale Group, Farmington Hills, Michigan.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
The entire collection, with the exception of Accession 2006-M-021 and Accession 2013-M-025, is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 248 instead of the originals.
Scope and Contents
A collection of correspondence; government documents, including reports, commissions, decrees, and awards; church documents; published illustrated materials; maps; and writings and poems from Mexico on civil, military, economic, religious, and social topics. Additions to the collection consist of photographs by Mario Bucovich, maps, and published illustrations, and trade union documents and publications.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two parts and two additions; materials in each part are arranged chronologically.
Archives -- Mexico; Artisans -- Mexico; Church and state -- Mexico -- History -- 19th century; Criminals -- Mexico; Customs administration -- Law and legislation -- Mexico; Deportation -- Mexico -- History -- 19th century; Education -- Mexico -- San Luis Potosí (Mexico: State); Education -- Mexico -- San Luis Potosí (Mexico); Education -- Mexico; Finance, Public -- Mexico; Guilds -- Mexico; Hospitals -- Mexico; Indians of Mexico; Intendants -- Mexico; Land tenure -- Mexico; Law -- Latin America; Lawyers -- Mexico; Liquor laws -- Mexico; Loans, British -- Mexico; Merchants -- Mexico; Mexican War, 1846-1848; Military law -- Mexico; Mineral industries -- Mexico; Missions -- Mexico; Monte de las Cruces, Battle of, Mexico, 1810; Municipal government -- Mexico; Newspapers -- Mexico; Notaries -- Mexico; Police -- Mexico; Public buildings -- Mexico; Silver mines and mining -- Mexico -- Pachuca; Silver mines and mining -- Mexico; Slavery -- Mexico; Smallpox; Smuggling; Street lighting -- Mexico; Tariff -- Law and legislation -- Mexico; Taxation -- Mexico; Taxation -- New Spain; Tobacco -- Mexico; Tobacco -- New Spain; Transportation -- Mexico; Wages -- Mexico; Acapulco (Mexico) -- History; Actopan (Veracruz-Llave, Mexico) -- History; Aguascalientes (Mexico) -- History; Campeche (Mexico: State) -- History; Catorce (Mexico) -- History; Celaya (Guanajuato, Mexico) -- History; Chiapas (Mexico) -- History; Chihuahua (Chihuahua, Mexico) -- History; Chihuahua (Mexico: State) -- History; Chilpancingo de los Bravos (Mexico) -- History; Cholula de Rivadabia (Mexico) -- History; Coahuila (Mexico: State) -- History; Coahuila and Texas (Mexico) -- History; Colombia -- Foreign relations -- Mexico; Cuautla Morelos (Mexico) -- History; Dolores Hidalgo (Guanajuato, Mexico) -- History; Durango (Mexico: State) -- History; France -- Foreign relations -- Mexico; Fresnillo de González Echeverría (Mexico) -- History; Guadalajara (Mexico) -- History; Guanajuato (Mexico) -- History; Guerrero (Mexico: State) -- History; Xalapa (Mexico) -- History; Linares (Nuevo León, Mexico) -- History; Mexico City (Mexico) -- History; Mexico -- Literatures; Mexico -- Administrative and political divisions; Mexico -- Armed Forces -- History; Mexico -- Church history; Mexico -- Description and travel; Mexico -- Economic conditions -- 1540-1810; Mexico -- Economic conditions -- 19th century; Mexico -- Economic reform -- 18th century; Mexico -- Foreign relations -- Colombia; Mexico -- Foreign relations -- France; Mexico -- Foreign relations -- Spain; Mexico -- Foreign relations -- United States; Mexico -- History -- 1821-1861; Mexico -- History -- 1867-1910; Mexico -- History -- 1910-1946; Mexico -- History -- Conquest, 1519-1540; Mexico -- History -- European intervention, 1861-1867; Mexico -- History -- Revolution, 1910-1920; Mexico -- History -- Spanish colony, 1540-1810; Mexico -- History -- Spanish Invasion, 1829; Mexico -- History -- Wars of Independence, 1810-1821; Mexico -- Politics and government -- 1540-1810; Mexico -- Politics and government -- 1810-1821; Mexico -- Politics and government -- 1821-1861; Mexico -- Politics and government -- 1861-1867; Mexico -- Politics and government -- 1867-1910; Mexico -- Social conditions -- 19th century; Mexico -- Social conditions -- To 1810; Mexico -- Social life and customs; Michoacán de Ocampo (Mexico) -- Church history; Michoacán de Ocampo (Mexico) -- History; Monclova (Mexico) -- History; Monterrey (Mexico) -- History; New Spain -- Church history; New Spain -- Commerce; New Spain -- Economic conditions; New Spain -- Laws, statutes, etc.; New Spain -- Officials and employees -- Salaries, etc.; New Spain -- Politics and government; Oaxaca (Mexico: State) -- History; Orizaba (Veracruz-Llave, Mexico) -- History; Pátzcuaro (Mexico) -- History; Provincias Internas (New Spain) -- History; Puebla de Zaragoza (Mexico) -- History; Querétaro (Mexico) -- History; Saltillo (Coahuila, Mexico) -- History; San Blas (Mexico) -- History; San Luis Potosí (Mexico: State) -- Economic conditions; San Luis Potosí (Mexico: State) -- History; San Luis Potosí (Mexico: State) -- Politics and government; San Luis Potosí (Mexico) -- History; Sierra Gorda (Mexico) -- History; Spain -- Colonies -- Administration; Spain -- Foreign relations -- Mexico; Spain -- History -- 18th century; Spain -- History -- Bourbons, 1700-; Tacubaya (Mexico City, Mexico) -- History; Tamaulipas (Mexico) -- History; Tampico (Tamaulipas, Mexico) -- History; Tehuacán (Mexico) -- History; Tlalpan (Mexico City, Mexico) -- History; Tlaxcala (Mexico: State) -- History; Toluca de Lerdo (Mexico) -- History; United States -- Foreign relations -- Mexico; Uruapan del Progreso (Mexico) -- History; Valladolid (Mexico) -- History; Veracruz (Veracruz-Llave, Mexico) -- History; Zacatecas (Zacatecas, Mexico) -- History; Zitácuaro (Mexico) -- History; Legal documents -- Mexico; Carlota, Empress, consort of Maximilian, Emperor of Mexico, 1840-1927; Charles, King of Spain, III, 1716-1788; Charles, King of Spain, IV, 1748-1819; Maximilian, Emperor of Mexico, 1832-1867; Pius, Pope, IX, 1792-1878; Abad y Queipo, Manuel, 1751-1825; Alamán, Lucas, 1792-1853; Allende, Ignacio, 1769-1811; Apodaca, Juan Ruiz de; Borda, José de la, 1699-1778; Branciforte, Miguel de la Grúa y Talamanca, marqués de, approximately 1755-1812; Brasseur de Bourbourg, abbé, 1814-1874; Bravo, Nicolás, 1786-1854; Bucovich, Mario, 1884-; Bustamante, Anastasio, 1780-1853; Bustamante, Carlos María de, 1774-1848; Calleja del Rey, Félix María, conde de Calderón, 1755?-1828; Cervantes de Salazar, Francisco, approximately 1514-approximately 1575; Comonfort, Ignacio, 1812-1863; Cordero y Bustamente, Manuel Antonio, 1753-1823; Cortés, Hernán, 1485-1547; Cos, José María, approximately 1770-1819; Croix, Teodoro de, 1730-1791; Cruz, José de la, 1786?-1856; Degollado, Santos, 1811-1861; Díaz, Porfirio, 1830-1915; Doblado, Manuel, 1818-1865; Domínguez, Miguel; Gálvez, José de, 1720-1787; Gamboa, Francisco Javier de, 1717-1794; Gómez Farías, Valentín, 1781-1858; González Pedraza, Manuel, 1789-1851; Guerrero, Vicente, 1782-1831; Herrera, José Joaquín de, 1792-1854; Hidalgo y Costilla, Miguel, 1753-1811; Iturbide, Agustín de, 1783-1824; Iturrigaray y Aróstegui, José de, 1742-1815; Juárez, Benito, 1806-1872; Lerdo de Tejada, Sebastián, 1823-1889; Liceaga, José María de, 1785-1870; Lizana y Beaumont, Francisco Javier, 1750-1811; López Rayón, Ignacio, 1773-1832; Mayer, Brantz, 1809-1879; Mejía, Tomás, 1820-1867; Michelena, José Mariano de, 1772-1852; Mier y Teran, Manuel de; Mina, Francisco Javier, 1789-1817; Miramón, Miguel, 1831-1867; Morelos, José María, 1765-1815; Negrete, Pedro Celestino, 1777-1846; Ocampo, Melchor, 1814-1861; O'Donojú, Juan, 1762-1821; Peña y Peña, Manuel de la, 1789-1850; Quintana Roo, Andrés, 1787-1851; Romero, Matías, 1837-1898; Santa Anna, Antonio López de, 1794?-1876; Talamantes, Melchor de, 1765-1809; Tornel y Mendívil, José María, 1789-1853; Torres, José Antonio, approximately 1760-1812; Venegas, Francisco Xavier, 1760-1838; Veytia, Mariano, 1718-1780?; Victoria, Guadalupe, 1786-1843; Vidaurri, Santiago, 1808-1867; Villavicencio, Pablo de; Zamacois, Niceto de, 1820-1885; Zavala, Lorenzo de, 1788-1836; Zuloaga, Félix, 1813-1898; New Spain. Real Audiencia (Mexico City); New Spain. Real Audiencia (Mexico City). Sala del Crimen; New Spain. Real Hacienda; New Spain. Tribunal de Minería; New Spain. Viceroy; Banco Nacional de Amortización (Mexico); Cárcel de Corte de la Nueva España -- History; Carmelites -- Mexico; Casa de Moneda de México; Catholic Church -- Missions -- Mexico; Catholic Church -- Mexico; Hospital Real de Indios (Mexico City, Mexico); Jesuits ( History 17th century); Jesuits ( History 18th century); Jesuits -- Mexico; Parián (Mexico City, Mexico)
- 1529-1907, Part I
  Scope and Contents
  Part I is 13.5 linear feet and is comprised of both originals and copies of government documents, including letters, decrees, edicts, ordinances, accounts and reports; church documents; correspondence; legal writs; political writings, and literary texts. The materials document the history of Mexico from the pre Columbian period to the beginning of the twentieth century, and illustrate the history of the peoples before the arrival of Spaniards; the Spanish conquest; the colonial civil and judicial administration; the role of the Catholic church in colonial society; the Bourbon reforms; the movement for independence; the First Mexican Empire; and the early republican period.
  On the history of the peoples who inhabited the Mexican territory before the arrival of Spaniards, the collection includes originals and copies of works written by authors in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. There are texts by the historian Mariano Fernández de Echeverria y Veytia and the travelers Brantz Mayer and Brasseur de Bourbourg. Concerning the Spanish conquest, the collection includes a copy of Crónica de la Nueva Espana by Francisco Cervantes de Salazar, the most prominent humanist in Mexico during the sixteenth century. Although unfinished, Cervantes's text is a detailed and fascinating account of the military enterprise of Hernán Cortes and his comrades.
  The texts concerning the colonial period, numerous and varied, constitute the core of the collection. To study the colonial civil administration during the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries, the reports written by viceroys and local authorities are valuable documents. The numerous legal writs are outstanding sources for understanding judicial administration and the literary culture of lawyers. Legal writs and decrees also provide rich information to analyze the economic, social and political significance of the Catholic church and the Jesuit, Franciscan, Dominican, Mercedarian, and Augustinian orders. The Bourbon reforms undertaken by colonial administration in the Mexican viceroyalty are extensively documented in the numerous royal and viceregal decrees, edicts, and ordinances promulgated mostly in the second half of the eighteenth century.
  On the independence movement, there are letters, reports, accounts and administrative texts by some of its leading protagonists, including Miguel Hidalgo y Costilla, Agusti?n de Itúrbide, and Viceroy José de Iturrigaray. The correspondence of the Iturbide family represents, for instance, an exceptional primary source documenting the social and political turmoil of that time. Additionally, the account written by Gregorio Melero y Piña, a follower of Miguel Hidalgo, is vivid personal testimony of military and political conspiracies in San Luis Potosi?. There are also original texts written about the political milieu by Carlos Mari?a Bustamante, the most important Mexican historian of the early nineteenth century.
  The history of the First Mexican Empire, established by Agusti?n de Itúrbide after independence was achieved, is documented generally in several letters and official reports which trace its establishment, political opposition to it, and the abdication of Itúrbide. On the initial decades of the Mexican Republic, there are diverse and numerous materials, including military and diplomatic reports, constitutional texts, and administrative papers.
  Conditions Governing Access
  The entire collection, with the exception of Accession 2006-M-021 and Accession 2013-M-025, is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 248 instead of the originals.
  - Title: Royal and viceregal decrees. Places: Mexico, Spain. Description: Five volumes of copies of royal and viceregal decrees concerning diverse matters such as military defense, commerce, religious orders, festivities and education of the Mexican viceroyalty. Some documents deal with administration and government of the city of Puebla.
    - Volume I, 1529-1812 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1)
    - Volume II
      - pp. 1-95 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1)
      - pp. 96-195 (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel 1)
    - Volume III
      - pp. 1-201 (Box 2, Folder 4, Reel 2)
      - pp. 202-334, plus unnumbered pages (Box 2, Folder 5, Reel 2)
    - Volume IV (Box 2, Folder 6, Reel 2)
    - Volume IV (Box 2, Folder 7, Reel 3)
    - Volume V (Box 3, Folder 8, Reel 3)
  - Author: Cervantes de Salazar, Francisco. Title: "Crónica de la Nueva España, su descripción, la calidad y temple de ella, la propiedad y naturaleza de los yndios." Place: Mexico City. Description: Humanist and historian, Francisco Cervantes de Salazar wrote this extensive, although incomplete, account of history of the Spanish conquest of Mexico around 1560. The account also contains information on geography, flora, fauna and native societies. This is a nineteenth century copy of the original preserved at the Royal Library in Madrid. [18--]
    - Libro 1-3 (Box 4, Folder 9, Reel 4)
    - Libro 4 (Box 5, Folder 10, Reel 5)
    - Libro 5 (Box 6, Folder 11, Reel 6)
  - Title: "Reales cédulas copiadas de un libro de la Real Audiencia que comprende desde el año de 1741 a 1750." Places: Mexico, Spain. Description: Copies of royal decrees, most of which are eighteenth century official documents on commerce, industry, political authorities and administration of the Mexican viceroyalty. 1563-1790 (Box 7, Folder 12, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal and viceregal decrees. Places: Mexico, Spain. Description: Copies of royal and viceregal decrees, most of which are late eighteenth century and early nineteenth century official documents on the government and administration of the Mexican viceroyalty. Includes an "Yndice alfabético de los bandos y órdenes que contiene este tomo." 1585-1818 (Box 7, Folder 13-14, Reel 7)
  - Title: Royal decrees. Place: Spain. Description: Copies and summaries of royal decrees, most of which are eighteenth century decrees addressed to the Royal Audiencia of Mexico concerning the administration of that viceroyalty. 1598-1776 (Box 8, Folder 15, Reel 8)
  - Author: Cortés, Hernán. Title: "Pide Cortés que se le envíen religiosos de buena vida y ejemplo para la conversión de los yndios y modo con que podían mantenerse y fabricar sus conbentos y de los arrendamientos de los diezmos." Place: Mexico? Description: Copy of a letter by the conqueror Hernán Cortés to the Emperor Charles V asking for missionaries to evangelize the native population of Mexico, and proposing to use tithes to support that religious enterprise. [15--] (Box 8, Folder 16, Reel 8)
  - Author: Quiroga, Vasco de. Title: "Reglas y ordenanzas para el gobierno de los hospitales de Santa Fe de México y Michoacán dispuestas por su fundador el reverendísimo y venerable señor don Vasco de Quiroga, primer obispo de Michoacán." Places: Michoacán? Rome. Description: Copies of the ordinances for the hospitals/towns of Indians founded by Vasco de Quiroga, bishop of Michoacán. Includes a copy of the Papal bull on the ordinances of the Michoacán bishopric. [15--] (Box 8, Folder 17, Reel 8)
  - Title: Legal writ. Place: Mexico City? Description: Legal writ related to the proceedings of Angela de Soria to recover the property of a hacienda which formerly belonged to her husband, Jerónimo Felipe Devas. [ca.1609] (Box 8, Folder 18, Reel 8)
  - Title: Documents on playing card monopoly. Places: Mexico, Madrid. Description: Documents concerning the administration of the playing card monopoly (estanco) in Mexico. 1620-1725 (Box 8, Folder 19, Reel 8)
  - Title: "Memorial de lo sucedido en la ciudad de México desde el dia primero de noviembre de 1623 hasta quinze de enero de 1624." Place: Mexico City? Description: Printed account of the social and political turmoil in Mexico city over the conflict between Viceroy Marquis of Gelves and Archbishop Juan Pérez de la Serna. 1623-1624 (Box 8, Folder 20, Reel 8)
  - Title: Documents on the Noviciate of Santa Ana. Place: Mexico city. Description: Nine documents concerning the dispute between the Society of Jesus and Maríana Niño de Aguilar over payment by the latter of 40,000 pesos to the Jesuit Noviciate of Santa Ana in Mexico City. Includes two printed texts: "Los fundamentos que favorecen a doña Maríana de Aguilar...en las excepciones propuestas para desvanecer la demanda del Padre Provincial de la Compañía de Jesús;" and "Jesús. María. Por la justicia de doña Maríana Niño de Aguilar...con el provincial de la Compañía de Jesús sobre el noviciado de Santa Ana." 1625-1640 (Box 8, Folder 21, Reel 8)
  - Title: Documents on the convent of Santo Domingo. Place: Mexico City? Description: Four documents related to the legal proceedings of the Convent of Santo Domingo to obtain payment of rent of houses it owned, located apparently in Mexico City. [ca.1632] (Box 8, Folder 22, Reel 8)
  - Title: Royal decree by the King. Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of a royal decree addressed to the General Inquisitor, issued on 30 May 1640, regulating disagreements between Tribunals of Inquisition and Royal Audiencias in cases of jurisdictional conflicts. The copy comes from the archive of the Mexican Inquisition. 1711 Oct 11 (Box 8, Folder 23, Reel 8)
  - Title: "Por don Alonso de Tapia Gusman y Castilla, en el pleito contra doña Maríana de Aguilar Niño, sobre una donación que le hizo de 3,420 pesos." Place: Mexico City? Description: Printed writ related to the legal proceedings of Alonso de Tapia Gusman y Castilla to revoke a judicial sentence which stated that the donation of 3,420 pesos made to him by Marina de Aguilar Niño was null and void. [ca.1644] (Box 8, Folder 24, Reel 8)
  - Title: "Por parte de don Fernando de Paz Cortez y Monroy, albacea de el licenciado don Gerónimo de Paz, difunto, en el pleyto con doña Madalena de Paz...sobre la donación." Place: Mexico City. Description: Printed writ related to the legal proceedings of Fernando de Paz Cortez y Monroy, testamentary executor of licenciate Gerónimo de Paz, against Madalena de Paz, who claimed to be the daughter of the latter. 1645 Nov 3 (Box 8, Folder 25, Reel 8)
  - Title: Edict by Juan de Mañozca, archbishop of Mexico. Place: Mexico City. Description: Printed edict issued by Juan de Mañozca, archbishop of Mexico, announcing that members of the Society of Jesus would start a campaign of indoctrination, devotional exercises, and preaching in the Mexican archbishopric. 1649 Nov 4 (Box 8, Folder 26, Reel 8)
  - Title: Four texts on the Society of Jesus. Places: Puebla, Rome, La Habana. Description: Book containing copies of four texts written in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries related to the Society of Jesus: "Carta del excelentísimo y venerable señor don Juan Palafox y Mendoza, obispo de la Puebla de los Angeles, escripta al Pontífize Ynnocencio X. Traducida del latín al castellano por el padre fray Andrés de la Visitación, religioso carmelita descalzo." (Puebla, 8 January 1649); "Oposición echa al progreso en las causas y procesos de la veatificación y canonización de el venerable siervo de Dios, el ilustrísimo y reverendísimo señor don Juan de Palafox y Mendoza, obispo que fue de la Puebla de los Angeles, en la Nueva España, y después de Osma en estos reinos de Castilla, y satisfacción a ella." by Tirso González (Rome, 26 July 1698); "Respuesta de un político de la Havana con fecha de 23 de septiembre de 1731 a un amigo suio de Lima que le escrivió una carta dándole noticia de la muerte de Joséph de Antequera." (La Habana, 23 September 1758); and "Carta de un cavallero romano cathólico a otro cavallero cathólico romano por un afecto a la verdad, antípoda de la ambición a petición de un curioso," by "Tu amigo el savio incógnito e ydiota bien conocido" (Rome, 28 December 1728). Although they vary in date, content and authorship, the four texts are similar in their critical opinion of the Society of Jesus. 1649-1758 (Box 8, Folder 27, Reel 8)
  - Title: Legal writs. Place: Mexico City. Description: Two legal writs related to the judicial proceedings of Nicolás Núñez Hidalgo to gain ownership of a fruit garden. 1650 (Box 9, Folder 28, Reel 8)
  - Title: "Reglas que han de guardar los congregantes de la Congregación de la Puríssima Concepción de Nuestra Señora la Virgen María fundada...en el Colegio de la Compañia de Jesús de San Pedro y San Pablo de la ciudad de México." Place: Mexico City. Description: Printed ordinances of the Confraternity of the Virgin Mary established in the Jesuit College in Mexico City. Describes devotional practices and duties of its members. On the reverse of the printed text there is the following manuscript note: "Al padre Prepósito de la casa profesa de la Compañía de Jesús." 1650 (Box 9, Folder 29, Reel 8)
  - Title: Legal writs. Place: Mexico city. Description: Three documents related to the legal proceedings of the Society of Jesus against Leonor de Rivera Valdes on the testamentary legacy of her sister, Gabriela de Rivera Valdes. Contains two printed texts: "Por la sagrada religión de la Compañía de Jesús desta ciudad;" and "Manifiesto por la Compañía de Jesús." 1651 (Box 9, Folder 30, Reel 8)
  - Title: Documents on ecclesiastical testaments. Places: Buen Retiro, Mexico. Description: Copy of a royal decree, issued on 18 June 1662, ordering that the publication of testaments and realization of inventories be reserved to civil judges. Includes the transcription of a legal writ on the inventory of holdings of Diego de las Heras, achdeacon of the cathedral of Antequera. 1662-1740 (Box 9, Folder 31, Reel 8)
  - Title: Royal decrees. Place: Spain. Description: Copies of royal decrees addressed to the viceroy and Royal Audiencia of Mexico concerning the economic and political administration of that viceroyalty. Most of the decrees were issued in the eighteenth century. 1662-1767 (Box 9, Folder 32, Reel 9)
  - Title: Letter by the Viceroy Marquis Count of Baños. Place: Mexico city. Description: Letter by Juan de Leyva y de la Cerda, viceroy Marquis Count of Baños, to the Royal Acuerdo, concerning a text written by Gines Morote critizing Leyva's administration. 1663 Dec 19 (Box 9, Folder 33, Reel 9)